创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
现在 所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了我们生存的限制
beyond the limits of our existence...
这个空间我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
小行星和彗星 地球的天上眷属
Asteroids and comets-- Earth's celestial relatives.
它们掌握着我们星球形成
They hold secrets to our planet's formation...
或许还有生命起源的秘密
and perhaps the origins of life.
小行星和彗星实际上可能担负着
Asteroids and comets may actually be responsible...
大量生命基石的搬运
for the delivery of a lot of the building blocks of life.
但是这些石块是行星的建造者和毁灭者
But these rocky bodies are planet builders and killers.
问题不在于我们在将来是否会遭受打击
The question is not whether we'll be struck in the future...
而是在何时何地
but when and where.
小行星和彗星乃头号宇宙杀手
Asteroids and comets remain cosmic enemy number one.
同时 它们会提供重要的资源
At the same time, they could provide vital resources...
有朝一日挽救人类免遭灭顶之灾
that could one day save humans from ultimate extinction.
宇宙:致命的彗星和流星
加利福尼亚的夏季
It's summertime in California.
人们一派忙忙碌碌
People go about their business...
并未察觉天上的动静
unaware of what's happening in the skies above.
没有任何征兆
Without any warning...
一个巨大的火球从天而降 犹如出膛的炮弹
a colossal fireball rockets down from space like a speeding bullet.
一旦撞击 毁灭性的破坏随之而来
Upon impact, apocalyptic destruction will ensue.
这不是真实的事件 但有可能发生
This is not a real life event, but it could be.
在亚利桑那大学
At the University of Arizona...
行星科学家杰伊.梅尔什及其同事
planetary scientist Jay Melosh and his colleagues...
开发了一个互动网站
have developed an interactive web site...
来评判小行星和彗星撞击地球的后果
for estimating the consequences...of asteroid and comet impacts on Earth.
网络用户可以创造自己的世界末日脚本
Web users can actually create their own doomsday scenarios.
每次撞击都会成为新闻
Every time impacts were in the news...
我会接到记者的电话
I'd get call from reporters...
他们想知道发生了什么事情
and they would want to know what would happen...
如果发生一定规模的撞击的话
if a certain size impact occurred.
我意识到这些都可以放到网站上
I realized that this could all be put in a web site...
这样任何人都可以来回答这些问题
so anyone could answer these questions themselves.
网络用户可以重建可怕的撞击事件
Web users can recreate actual chilling impact events...
甚至是墨西哥湾那样规模的
even the massive one in the Gulf of Mexico...
那是6500万年前
that triggered the mass extinction of the dinosaur...
造成了恐龙的大规模灭绝
over 65 million years ago.
我们来假设杀死恐龙的撞击
Let's suppose that the dinosaur-killing impact...
不是发生在尤卡坦半岛 而是发生在洛杉矶
occurred not in Yucatan, but in Los Angeles...
而我们生活在旧金山
and we're living in San Francisco...
我们想知道究竟会发生些什么
and we want to find out what happens.
为了模拟洛杉矶的撞击事件
In order to simulate the impact event in Los Angeles...
梅尔什输入了以下数据:
Melosh enters the following data:
撞击物的直径
projectile diameter...
撞击的速度与角度
impact velocity and angle...
目标类型 诸如水面还是岩石地表
target type, such as water or rocky surface...
与撞击点的距离
and distance from the impact.
计算机程序现在就来告诉我们
The computer program will now tell us...
我们在旧金山这里的感受
what we feel here in San Francisco.
计算影响
"Calculate effects."
在旧金山 我们可以看到这个大火球
As far away as San Francisco, we can see this huge fireball...
出现在撞击点上空
that develops over the impact site.
其能量超过了
The energy is bigger...
全球核武库的总和
than all the world's arsenals of nuclear weapons combined.
这次撞击的结果
As a result of this impact...
洛杉矶被彻底抹去了
Los Angeles is completely obliterated.
接下来 撞击爆发出的岩石碎片
Next, rock debris blasted out by the impact...
射入了大气层
travels ballistically above the atmosphere...
然后再次落下覆盖我们这地方
and then reenters over our location.
旧金山将遭受重创
San Francisco will get fried...
被埋在24英寸厚的碎屑下
and then buried by 24 inches of debris.
高架公路垮塌
Highway trusses will collapse.
多层建筑垮塌
Multi-story buildings will collapse.
旧金山不是
San Francisco will not be a good place to be...
应对这么大撞击的理想之地
for an impact this big.
这个互动网站
This interactive web site...
貌似世界末日的视频游戏
may seem like a video game of Armageddon...
但它实际上是严肃的科学
but it's actually serious science...
作为一种警示
and serves as a warning...
有关小行星和彗星撞击究竟会有多大危害
about how dangerous asteroid and comet impacts could be.
这不是卡通或玩模拟游戏
This isn't a cartoon or play simulation.
撞击的影响全都收集在一起
The impact effects are all compiled...
包括诸如核武器手册
from things like nuclear weapons manuals...
地震得到的经验之类的东西
by experience from Earthquakes...
这样我们尽力做得最好
and so we've done the best job we possibly could...
用上所有最好的现代科技
with all the best modern technology...
来获得其结果的准确描述
to get an accurate description of what happens.
纵贯地球史
Throughout Earth's history...
小行星和彗星一直就是死亡信使
asteroids and comets have been messengers of death.
与此同时 它们也有可能一直是生命的引渡人
At the same time, they may also have been deliverers of life.
约45亿年前
Approximately 4.5 billion years ago...
我们太阳系看上去就像是宇宙射击场
our solar system looked like a cosmic shooting gallery...
天体岩石相撞兼并成行星
as celestial rocks collided and coalesced to form planets.
太阳系形成后
After our solar system was formed...
没有形成行星或卫星的太空石块
space rocks that didn't mold into planets or moons...
就变成了无人管束的垃圾
became wayward debris.
在我们太阳系内部 数以百万计的残留石块
Within our inner solar system, millions of these leftover rocks...
构成了小行星带
became part of the asteroid belt...
在木星与火星之间围绕着太阳运转
that orbits around the Sun between Jupiter and Mars.
我们认为木星的强大引力
We think that the powerful gravity of Jupiter...
强大到足以防止这些小行星体
was strong enough to prevent these planetesimals...
粘合在一起形成更大的物体
from sticking together to form even larger objects...
就是我们所谓的真正的行星
that we would consider a real planet.
因此 对于小行星带
So the asteroid belt...
你可能会以为它是失败行星的收集地
you might think of it as a collection of failed planets.
小行星通常形状不规则
Asteroids are typically irregular-shaped...
布满了撞击坑
and pitted with impact craters.
其大小范围 从微小的尘埃颗粒
They range in size from tiny dust grains...
到直径数百英里不等
to hundreds of miles in diameter.
因为它们是与地球同时形成的
Because they were formed at the same time as Earth...
小行星的基本元素
asteroids contain the same basic elements...
与我们星球上看到的并无不同
we find on our planet to build things.
科学家艾米.迈因策尔
Research scientist Amy Mainzer...
在一家直升机工厂里找到了宇宙物质
has located cosmic material in a helicopter factory.
这架直升机里的成分
The components of this helicopter here...
实际上与我们在所有小行星里找到的元素
are actually shockingly similar to the elemental constituents...
惊人地相似
we find in all different types of asteroids.
钢支架 钢发动机缸体
The steel struts and the steel engine block...
主要成分是铁
which is mostly made of iron...
我说 玻璃纤维板 主要是硅和氧
and, say, the fiberglass panels, mostly silicon and oxygen...
还有铝外壳
and the aluminum sheeting.
同样 有些小行星也有类似的区分
Also, some asteroids are similarly differentiated...
你可以看到有金属铁镍核心
where you have a metallic iron-nickel core...
包裹着一层硅酸盐
surrounded by a layer of silicates...
各种物质组成了外壳
and various combinations of other materials in the shell.
这架直升机完成总装后
When the final assembly of this helicopter is complete...
就像是小行星 动起来了
just like the asteroids, it moves.
宛如直升机把人们送到我们星球各地一样
Just as helicopters transport people all around our planet...
小行星和彗星
asteroids and comets transport material...
也会将物质送到太阳系各地
throughout our solar system.
小行星和彗星的指纹
Asteroids are cosmic fingerprints...
揭示了地球昔日所失踪的线索
that reveal missing clues about Earth's past.
撞击后
Fragments of asteroids...
幸存在地球表面的小行星碎片
that actually survive an impact with the Earth's surface...
称为陨石
are called meteorites.
大多数是在干旱的沙漠或极地地区找到的
Most have been recovered in dry deserts or polar regions...
在那里 这些黑暗的石块较易发现
where these dark rocks are easier to detect.
在航天局约翰逊航天中心 科学家迈克尔.泽伦斯基
At NASA's Johnson Space Center, scientist Michael Zolensky...
收集分析这些陨石
has collected and analyzed meteorites.
从南极带回来了有4万多块陨石
There's more than 40,000 meteorites been brought back from Antarctica.
这两块陨石 我们认为它们来自小行星
These are two meteorites, and we think they're from asteroids.
看这里 这块是碳质球粒陨石
Right here, this is a carbonaceous chondrite...
这个是普通球粒陨石
and this is an ordinary chondrite.
这些是现在掉落在地球上最常见的陨石种类
These are the most common kinds of meteorites that fall to Earth today.
它们含有大量铁 镁 硅酸盐
And they contain a lot of iron, magnesium, silicates...
这些你可以在地球上见到
things you see in the Earth.
因此小行星给我们讲述了最早的行星构建史
So the asteroids tell us about the earliest history of planet building.
这里我们就有了小小的实验室
Here we have little, little laboratories...
来研究行星在其早期的演化
for studying how planets evolved early in their history.
小行星并非地球形成的
And asteroids aren't the only remnants...
唯一残留物
from the formation of planet Earth.
在寒冷的外太阳系里
In the frigid outer solar system...
剩余的石块现在都在柯伊伯带里
leftover rocks now orbit neatly in the Kuiper Belt...
就在海王星外边
just beyond planet Neptune.
我们认为在外太阳系里
We believe in the outer solar system...
冰和尘埃堆积在一起
ice and dust accumulated together...
形成大量较小的天体
into a large number of smaller bodies...
它们的轨道受到大行星的干扰
whose orbits were disturbed by the giant planets...
它们最终被驱散
and they were eventually scattered out...
进入我们现在所谓的柯伊伯带里
into what we now call the Kuiper Belt.
过去 主题思想是
In the past, the main idea was...
彗星的形成远离太阳
that comets formed farther from the Sun.
那是因为
And because of that...
彗星含有大量挥发性的元素:
the comets retained a larger amount of volatile elements:
冰 固态水 固态一氧化碳
ices and frozen water and frozen carbon monoxide...
诸如此类的东西 以及有机物
and things like that and more organics.
小行星一般来说很少有此类东西
And the asteroids as a whole had fewer of those things.
这些冰体不光在柯伊伯带里有
These icy bodies are not only located in the Kuiper Belt.
正在形成中的太阳
The forming Sun flung comets...
将彗星抛到太阳系的外围
to the outer reaches of the solar system...
打造了一个球形的深冻区
which created a spherical deep-freeze reservoir...
叫做奥尔特云
known as the Oort Cloud.
奥尔特云距离太阳有两光年
The Oort Cloud is up to a couple of light-years...away from the Sun.
奇怪的是 尽管奥尔特云距离太阳比柯伊伯带更远
Strangely enough, even though the Oort Cloud...is farther away from the Sun than the Kuiper Belt...
但是我们认为 它有可能实际上是形成于
we think that it may have actually formed...
太阳系内部
inside the inner parts of the solar system.
事实上 其原因就在于
In fact, the reason for this...
我们在彗星内部所发现的某些物质
is that some of the materials we find inside comets...
有可能只是在高温下形成的
could only have been formed with high heat.
今天 我们来打造一个彗星
So today, we are building a comet.
我们将从把水倒进碗里开始
We're going to start off by pouring the water into the bowl.
用水是因为彗星是由固态水构成的
The water is used because comets are made up of water ice.
因此我们开始就用上一点水
So we start off with some water.
接下来的事情是加进两勺尘埃
The next thing we're going to add is a couple of teaspoons of dirt.
彗星含有大量的尘埃 真的
Comets contain a lot of dirt, actually.
尘埃里含有各种矿物质
Dirt consists of various minerals of different types...
含有各种重元素 比如铁
containing all kinds of heavy elements such as iron.
下来 我们要加进少许玉米糖浆
Next, we're going to add a little bit of corn syrup.
玉米糖浆里含有碳 氢和氧
Corn syrup here consists of carbons, hydrogens, and oxygens...
那是我们在彗星里发现的
that we find inside of comets.
下来 我们要加进一些玻璃清洁剂
Next, we're going to add some of this window cleaner.
这种玻璃清洁剂里有一种主要成分是氨
One of the main ingredients inside this window cleaner...
那是我们在彗星里发现的另一种常见的
is ammonia, which is another common chemical...
化学物质
found inside comets.
好了 我们要将这些原料混合在一起
Okay, we're going to mix all these ingredients up...
放进我们的搅拌碗里
inside our mixing bowl...
现在我们准备加入干冰了
and now we're ready to start adding the dry ice.
现在你可以看到
And you can see here...
我们塑料袋里的这些东西开始冻结了
we're starting to freeze all of this stuff inside our plastic bag.
好唻 现在我们有了我们的彗星了
All right. And here we have our comet.
你可以看到 就像是个真正的彗星
And you can see, like a real comet...
它不是特别圆
it's not particularly round.
它相当粗糙 凹凸不平 包裹着尘埃
It's pretty lumpy and craggy and covered with dirt.
如果我们用这盏灯来代表太阳
So if we use this light to represent the Sun...
我们就可以看到阳光
we can see what the effect...
对我们的彗星所产生的影响
of sunlight on our comet is going to have.
你看到的情景是
And you can see what's happening...
暖和的灯光开始蒸发气体
is the warm light is starting to evaporate the gases.
由于彗星围绕太阳运转
So as a comet travels around the Sun...
太阳发出的热量开始蒸发出
the heat from the Sun starts to vaporize...
一些挥发性的有机物质
some of its volatile organic materials...
它开始将它们丢失进长长的尾巴里
and it starts to lose them in a long tail...
在彗星身后延展很远的距离
that can extend out very far beyond the comet.
1986年 乔托探测器
In 1986, the Giotto spacecraft...
成为了掠过彗星的首次造访
became the first mission to fly by a comet.
它就是哈雷彗星
It was Comet Halley...
是已知在人的一生中唯一回来一次的
the only one known to return within our human lifetime...
也是肉眼所能见到的
and that is also visible to the naked eye.
造访揭示哈雷彗星满载着
The mission revealed that Halley is laden...
数百万亿磅的分子
with several hundred trillion pounds...
那是地球生命最需要的: 水
of the molecule needed most by life on Earth: water.
基于这次发现和以往的研究
Based on this discovery and previous research...
天文学家推测 那些冰体
astronomers speculate that these icy bodies...
有可能掌握着地球之水
may hold clues to the source of water on Earth...
乃至生命来源的线索
and perhaps even life.
水
Water...
覆盖了地球表面的三分之二
it blankets over two-thirds of Earth's surface.
它滋养了植物和动物 包括人类
It nourishes plants and animal life, including man.
但是这水有可能是来自太空吗?
But could this water have come from outer space?
起初 科学家认为冰彗星
Initially, scientists thought that icy comets...
有可能在我们太阳系形成期间
might have supplied most of Earth's water...
提供了地球的大部分水
during the formation of our solar system.
然而 新的研究表明
However, new research suggests...
彗星可能不是我们星球的水的主要来源
that comets may not have been the primary source...for our planet's water.
我们地球的海洋里包含了H2O 普通的水
Our Earth's oceans contain a combination of H2O, normal water...
以及HDO 即重水 其中含有氘
and HDO, or heavy water, which includes deuterium...
一种罕见的氢 它多出了一个中子
a rare variety of hydrogen that has an extra neutron.
结果是 我们目前所观察到的彗星
It turns out that the comets we've looked at so far...
氘对氢的比例
the deuterium-to-hydrogen ratio...
约比地球海洋高出两倍
is about two times higher than that of Earth's oceans.
因此 不是非常的匹配
So it isn't such a good match.
科学家尚没有完全排除彗星
Scientists haven't completely ruled out comets.
但是会不会是石质小行星就是地球之水的来源呢?
But could rocky asteroids have been a source of Earth's water?
所谓的碳质球粒陨石类小行星
The so-called carbonaceous chondrite types of asteroids...
一般出现在
which are typically found...
小行星带的最外层
in the outermost reaches of the main asteroid belt...
它们的氘对氢的比例与地球海洋
have an almost exact match...
几乎能完全匹配
between their deuterium-to-hydrogen ratios and Earth's oceans.
碳质球粒陨石类小行星的重水之所以少于彗星
Carbonaceous chondrite asteroids...may have less heavy water than comets...
原因就是它们形成于较高的温度
due to the higher temperatures at which they were formed...
因为它们距离太阳更近
since they're closer to the Sun.
水的主要来源几乎肯定是
The main source of water is almost certainly...
近地小行星的碰撞
near-Earth asteroids that have collided...
释放出大量的水蒸汽
and given off large quantities of water vapor...
然后只要条件允许 就会在地球上凝结成水
which then, when conditions allowed, condensed as water on Earth.
地球之水另一个可能的来源
Another possible source of Earth's water...
有可能已经确定为
may have been identified with the discovery...
在小行星带里所发现的三个新的物体
of three peculiar new objects in the asteroid belt.
最近 科学家发现了
Recently, scientists have discovered...
令人兴奋的新一类物体 叫做主带彗星
an exciting new category of object called the main-belt comets.
它们看上去像彗星
They look like a comet.
它们有一个核 四周是慧发
They have a nucleus, surrounded by a hazy coma...
拖着长长的尾巴
with a long tail extending out.
然而 它们的轨道动力学
However, their orbital dynamics...
让它们完全呆在主小行星带里
keep them entirely within the main asteroid belt.
所以根据它们的轨道动力学 它们看上去就像是小行星
So from their orbital dynamics, they look like asteroids.
或许地球海洋的来源
Perhaps the origin of the Earth's oceans...
有可能就是这些主带彗星
could be these main-belt comets...
它们具有高含量的水
which have high concentrations of water...
以及其它有机物质
and other organic materials.
科学家们仍然在争论是小行星还是彗星
Scientists are still debating whether asteroids or comets...
把水送到了地球
could have delivered water to Earth.
更大的谜团
And the bigger mystery...
就是它们是否还送来了
is whether they also could have delivered...
生命的要素
the essential elements for life.
彗星和小行星都含有有机物质
Comets and asteroids both contain organic matter.
它们都多次撞击过地球
They both repeatedly strike Earth.
它们无疑会带来有机物质
They certainly brought in organic matter.
有多少溶解于水了 并有可能发展成了生命
How much was dissolved in water and permitted the development of life...
我们不得而知
we don't know.
陨石中已经发现了70多种氨基酸
Over 70 kinds of amino acids have been found in meteorites.
许多是构成生命细胞蛋白质的
Many are the fundamental ingredients of proteins...
基本要素
that make up living cells.
我们最近在两块陨石中发现了
We recently found tiny, little microscopic globules...
细微的球状碳氢化合物
of hydrocarbons in a couple of meteorites...
这些或许是完整的细胞原型
and these would be perfect precursors to cells.
想象一下 这些东西早期落在地球
Imagine these things are falling on the Earth...
或其他地方
or anywhere else early in its history...
为有机反应的发生提供了一个现成的小家
providing ready-made little homes for organic reactions to occur in.
研究宇宙石块是否带来了水
Another way to study whether cosmic rocks...
以及地球潜在生命的另一个途径
delivered water and possibly life to Earth...
是收集太空尘埃
is by collecting space dust.
每天都有上百吨细微的宇宙和小行星物质
A hundred tons of microscopic comet and asteroid material...
落在地球上
rains down on us every day.
航天局的高空飞机项目
NASA's High Altitude Aircraft Program...
一直在地球6.5万英尺高的平流层里
has been collecting uncontaminated cosmic dust grains...
收集未受污染的宇宙尘埃颗粒
in the stratosphere over 65,000 feet above Earth.
这架飞机收集微粒
The aircraft collects microscopic particles...
靠的是安装在翅膀上的硅油粘性采集器
on silicon oil-coated sticky plate collectors on the wings.
它有点像石蜡
It's a little like paraffin wax.
这样飞机飞经平流层
So planes are flying through the stratosphere...
会有小颗粒慢慢飘落
here's a little particle slowly drifting down...
飞机飞过时 它就会掉入这个石蜡里
and the plane just flies up, and it just smacks into this paraffin...
会站在那里 就像蝇拍上的苍蝇一样
and it gets stuck there like a fly on a fly swatter.
这些高海拔实验显示
These high-altitude experiments have revealed...
星际尘埃和地球
that interplanetary dust and the Earth...
都是由相同的硅酸盐颗粒构成的
are both made up of the same silicate grains...
那在太阳系早期必定就已经存在了
that must have been present during the early solar system.
因此或许它们帮助送来了生命的基石
So perhaps they helped to deliver the building blocks for life.
高空飞行已经让航天局着手开展
The high-altitude flights have prepared NASA...
一项最具雄心的任务
to embark on one of its most ambitious missions.
1981年 科学家开始研究
In 1981, scientists began researching...
如何去收集名为威尔德二号的彗星附近的碎片
how to collect actual pieces from a nearby comet named Wild 2...
那是颗在火星轨道内运行的彗星
which was traveling within the orbit of Mars.
我们这次任务
The fundamental question we were trying to address...
试图解决的基本问题是
with this mission was...
这颗彗星威尔德二号 究竟有没有液态水
did this comet, Wild 2, ever have liquid water?
我们知道它有大量的固态水
We know it had lots of water ice.
所有的彗星都有 但是它们总是很冷的
All comets do, but were they always cold...
抑或它们会不会内部升温
or did they perhaps heat up inside...
将冰融化成液态水呢?
to melt this water ice to liquid water?
那确实很重要 因为一旦你有了液态水
That's really important because once you have liquid water...
你就会看到生命之类的东西了
then you could have things like life.
科学家面临严峻的挑战
Scientists were faced with a daunting challenge.
分离阶段完成
Stage separation has occurred...
进行第二阶段点火
and we have second-stage ignition.
飞船如何才能收集到未受污染的彗星碎片
How could the spacecraft collect untainted pieces of a comet...
其移动的速度是子弹的10倍
that would be moving ten times as fast as a speeding bullet...
因此 它会产生巨大的热量
and, therefore, generating tremendous heat?
试想一下 试图停下在飞行途中的子弹来研究它
So imagine, then, trying to stop a rifle bullet in mid-flight to study it...
同时又要不破坏子弹 不破坏你自己
without destroying the rifle bullet and without destroying you.
你如何去做到呢? 这就是我们的问题
How would you do that? That was our problem.
解决之道就是使用气凝胶
The solution was to use Aerogel...
一种二氧化硅制成的脆弱的多孔物质
a fragile, porous substance made from silicon dioxide.
比棉花球还轻
Lighter than a cotton ball...
气凝胶具有热绝缘特性
Aerogel contains thermal-insulating properties...
要强于窗户玻璃
that are stronger than window glass.
你好 彼得 欢迎来奥尔德卡斯尔玻璃公司
Hello, Peter. Welcome to Oldcastle Glass.
很高兴你能光临
Glad you could make it.
航天局的彼得.邹博士发现气凝胶
NASA scientist Dr. Peter Tsou discovered that Aerogel...
可以捕捉到高温高速的彗星粒子
could capture hot, fast-moving cometary particles...
并伤害很小
with minimal damage.
你在这里看到的玻璃
The glass that you see here...
气凝胶的热绝缘特性
the heat insulating properties of Aerogel...
超过玻璃上百倍
is more than a hundred times better than glass...
因为玻璃是固体材料
because glass is solid material.
气凝胶主要是空气 因此导热不是很理想
Aerogel mostly is air, so it doesn't conduct heat very well...
因此它是良好的绝缘体
so it's a better insulator.
我这里有一块气凝胶
l have a piece of Aerogel here...
有一些蜡笔
and l have some crayons.
我将它放在气凝胶的上面
I'll put it on top of this Aerogel.
这里我要用火把来证明
So I'm going to use a torch...
加热这块气凝胶
to demonstrate that heating this piece of Aerogel...
能够对绝缘的 因此蜡笔是不会融化的
will be able to insulate it so the crayon won't melt.
燃烧了 它是绝缘的 蜡笔完好无损
It is burning, it's insulating that, and the crayon is still intact.
它没有融化
It doesn't melt.
气凝胶可能是地球上适当的热绝缘体
Aerogel may be a suitable thermal insulator on Earth...
但是这种材料可不可以拿到太空呢?
but would the substance hold up in space?
2004年1月4日
On January 2, 2004...
航天局的星尘号飞船遇上了威尔德二号彗星
NASA's Stardust spacecraft met up with Comet Wild 2.
在接近其尘埃云即慧发时
Upon approaching its dust cloud or coma...
飞船弹开一个桨形收集盘
the craft flipped open a paddle-shaped collector tray...
其中有冰块大小的气凝胶片
containing ice cube-sized pieces of Aerogel.
方案就是以1.3万英里的时速
The plan was to capture cometary particles...
来捕捉彗星微粒
moving at over 13,000 miles per hour.
飞船最后返回地球时
When the spacecraft finally returned to Earth...
约翰逊航天中心里一派紧张兴奋的气氛
nervous excitement filled the air at Johnson Space Center.
我就是那个取出那收集盘的人
I was the one to pick up the tray.
事实上 我取出盘子
In fact, when I picked it up in there...
心里忐忑不安
I was a little bit scared.
要是我取出收集盘 里面一无所有怎么办?
What if l pick up the tray, there's nothing there?
我开始冒汗了
I was...broke in a sweat.
当我把它翻过来一看 哇
When l turned it around and looked at it, wow...
我看到了三四十个微粒 我肉眼都看到了
I saw about three dozen particles I could see with the naked eye.
惊奇 太惊奇了 好了不起
It's amazing. Amazing. Nice work.
进一步分析星尘号的样本
Further analysis of the Stardust samples...
也许会有朝一日揭示地球之水
may one day reveal whether Earth's water...
乃至生命是否来自宇宙
or perhaps life, came from comets.
不过他们已经准备深刻了解
But they've already provided insight...
小行星和彗星之间惊人的相似之处
into the striking similarities between asteroids and comets.
许多微粒含有丰富的碳氢化合物
Many particles contained abundant hydrocarbons...
那是彗星通常所在的外太阳系那样的
that couldn't have formed in the cold environment...
寒冷的环境中所无法形成的
where comets typically reside in the outer solar system.
我们从彗星盘里得到了气凝胶样本
We have the Aerogel samples from the cometary tray.
我们多半会认为这些微粒形成于
We mostly thought these grains would've formed...
远离太阳 彗星形成的地方
out far from the Sun where the comet formed.
我们发现某些彗星微粒
We find that some of the grains in the comet...
必须形成在靠近太阳表面的地方
must have formed right up next to the Sun's surface...
被加热到超过1000度 甚至2000度
heated to over 1,000 degrees, maybe 2,000 degrees.
经过一番分析 科学家在琢磨
After much analysis, scientists wondered...
某些彗星究竟是不是在假冒小行星呢?
do some comets actually masquerade as asteroids?
航天局的下一个任务就是解决这个回避不了的问题
NASA's next mission would tackle that question head-on.
小行星
Asteroids...
和彗星
and comets...
曾被认为是风马牛不相及的宇宙物体
once thought to be very different cosmic bodies...
有可能关系密切超出原先的想象
may be more closely related than previously thought.
2005年 航天局的深度撞击号飞行器
In 2005, NASA's Deep Impact spacecraft...
发射了一颗炮弹撞击一颗坦普尔1号的彗星核
launched a projectile into the nucleus of a comet named Tempel 1.
科学家首次捕捉到了
For the first time, scientists captured images...
彗星冰冻泥泞的内核图像
of a comet's icy, muddy interior.
我们认为彗星星表下面的物质
We think that material that's underneath the comet's surface...
实际上处于彗星形成时的原始状态
is really in a pristine state from when the comet was first formed...
可能是几十亿年前的
which could be billions of years ago.
深度撞击任务
The Deep Impact mission...
证明了某些彗星确实是在假冒小行星
concluded that some comets actually mimic asteroids.
彗星围绕太阳好多圈后
After a comet orbits around the Sun many times...
会失去其冰冷的气体成分
it loses its icy, gaseous components.
它基本上变成了休眠状
It essentially becomes dormant...
显示出干燥的表面
showing a dry surface...
貌似碳质球粒陨石小行星
that resembles a carbonaceous chondrite asteroid...
含有大量的含水矿物质
which contains many water-bearing minerals.
我们现在研究陨石 总是假设
We're looking at meteorites now which we always assumed...
它只是来自小行星 疑惑的是 知道吗
always just came from asteroids, and wondering, you know...
其中有可能是来自彗星吗?
which of these could have come from comets?
它告诉我们的是存在着好多种彗星
What that tells us is that there are many different kinds of comets.
它们有着不同的历史 就像小行星那样
They've all had different histories, just like asteroids have.
小行星和彗星的共同点远不止
Asteroids and comets have much more in common...
物理和化学成分
than just physical and chemical composition.
它们都给地球留下了累累伤痕
They've both left deep scars on Earth...
造成生命的灭绝
which have resulted in the extermination of life...
一而再 再而三
time and time again.
近地物体是小行星和彗星
Near-Earth objects are asteroids and comets...
它们的轨道带着它们靠近地球的轨道
whose orbits bring them close to Earth's orbit.
就小行星来说
In the case of asteroids...
木星的引力和太阳的光压
Jupiter's gravity or light pressure from the Sun...
会将这些宇宙残骸撞出小行星带
can bump these cosmic relics out of the asteroid belt.
同样 海王星的引力
Similarly, the gravity from planet Neptune...
也会将彗星推出柯伊伯带
can nudge comets out of the Kuiper Belt.
小行星撞击的疤痕
The scars from asteroid impacts...
在太阳系里比比皆是
can be seen throughout our solar system.
所有类地行星和卫星
All the terrestrial planets and moons...
都有这些致命打击的烙印 包括地球
show the marks of these deadly blows, including Earth.
6500万年前 一个约6英里宽的宇宙物体
65 million years ago, a cosmic object roughly six miles across...
撞击了尤卡坦半岛
impacted the Yucatan Peninsula...
就在现在的墨西哥希克苏鲁伯村庄附近
near the modern village of Chicxulub, Mexico.
其产生的动能
It produced kinetic energy...
相当于八十亿颗广岛原子弹
equivalent to eight billion Hiroshima atomic bombs.
撞击事件在海底留下了 一个超过110英里直径的陨石坑
The impact event left a crater in the ocean over 110 miles across...
比大峡谷深20倍
and 20 times as deep as the Grand Canyon.
由于这个撞击事件同时击中大海
Because the impact event hit the sea simultaneously...
它引起了滔天海啸
this created tsunami-size ripples...
席卷墨西哥墨西哥湾海岸
that then crashed onto the shoreline of the Gulf of Mexico.
能量和陨石坑里物质的喷发之剧烈
The energy and the explosive ejection of that material from the crater...
以至于融化的碎片
was so dramatic that that molten debris...
覆盖了整个北美
actually blanketed all of North America.
我们所知的生命几乎都遭到了灭顶之灾
Life as we know it would have been virtually erased.
现在许多科学家认为 该撞击事件
Many scientists now believe the impact event...
抹去了陆地上和海洋里的75%的动植物种
extinguished 75 percent of animal and plant species...
包括恐龙
on land and sea, including the dinosaurs.
行星地质学家大卫.克林
Planetary geologist David Kring...
是最著名的小行星撞击事件专家之一
is one of the foremost experts on asteroid impact events.
我们现在明白了撞击事件
We now understand that impact events...
不单是个挖出一个碗状坑洞的地质过程
aren't simply a geologic process...that excavates a bowl-shaped cavity...
而实际上会影响到环境
but one that actually can affect the environment...
无论其当个别地方 地区还是全球性的
whether it be local, regional, or global.
2001年 克林主管希克苏鲁伯科学钻探项目
In 2001, Kring headed up...the Chicxulub Scientific Drilling Project...
就在尤卡坦半岛撞击点附近
near the impact site in the Yucatan Peninsula.
克林的目标是寻找证据 证明希克苏鲁伯撞击
Kring's goal was to find evidence that the Chicxulub impact...
会产生全球气候影响
produced worldwide climate effects...
通过钻入可追溯到当时的岩石
by drilling down to the rock dating to that time period.
钻探项目证实了我们的质疑
The drilling project confirmed our suspicions...
该撞击事件已经撞击到了
that the impact event had collided...
一系列非常重要的岩石类型:
with a series of very important rock types:
石灰石和硬石膏
limestone and anhydrite.
石灰岩 蒸发时会产生...
The limestone, when vaporized...
温室气体 二氧化碳
produced greenhouse-warming carbon dioxide...
而硬石膏 蒸发时 会产生硫酸雨
and the anhydrite, when vaporized, produced sulfuric acid rain...
因此这就证明了
and so this confirmed...
希克苏鲁伯撞击事件
some of the global climatic effects produced...
带来了某种全球气候影响
by the Chicxulub impact event.
希克苏鲁伯科学钻探项目
The Chicxulub Scientific Drilling Project...
还揭示出撞击生成的热液系统
also revealed that the impact generated hydrothermal systems...
覆盖了整个陨石坑
that span the entire diameter of the crater.
这一过程为新生命演化提供了
These processes provided critical environments...
关键的环境
for new life to evolve.
6500年前
The extinction of the dinosaurs...
恐龙的灭绝和其它生命的消失
and the other life that disappeared 65 million years ago...
创造了新的环境和生态位
created new environmental and ecological niches.
这样幸存者得以演化
So the survivors were able to evolve...
把握新的机遇
and take hold of those new opportunities.
随后的演化导致了
The subsequent evolution has led to the formation...
我们人类的形成乃至进化
or the evolution of our own species, the human species.
下一次希克苏鲁伯规模的撞击
The next Chicxulub-sized impact...
预计会发生在3500万年后
is estimated to occur 35 million years from now...
但是谁也无法确定大难何时临头
but one can never be too certain when it comes to space rocks.
不幸的是 此类事情不会像时钟那样掐得准
Unfortunately, these types of things do not occur like clockwork.
事实上 下一次希克苏鲁伯规模的撞击事件
In fact, the next Chicxulub-size impact event...
有可能就发生在明天
could occur tomorrow.
许多科学家相信
Many scientists are confident that a cosmic impact...
宇宙事件是恐龙灭绝的肇因
was responsible for wiping out the dinosaur...
但是他们仍在为何种石块而争论不休
but they're still debating about what type of rock.
我们实际上还没有确定究竟是小行星撞击
We aren't actually sure whether this was an impacting asteroid...
还是彗星撞击
or an impacting comet...
尽管大量的证据点指向小行星
although the bulk of the evidence points towards an asteroid.
小行星事实上左右着撞击地球的碎片量
Asteroids, in fact, dominate the flux...of impacting debris to the Earth.
约莫有85%到95%的撞击地球的物体
Somewhere on the order of 85 to 95 percent...of the objects that collide with the Earth...
是来自主小行星带
come from the main asteroid belt.
如果我们发现有彗星处于威胁地球的轨道上
If we do find a comet on an Earth-threatening trajectory...
在其造成毁灭性打击之前
it could be difficult to deflect or destroy...
极可能难以对其偏离或摧毁
before it inflicts apocalyptic destruction.
近地物体是小行星
Near-Earth objects are asteroids...
并已经脱离了小行星带进入了
that have been dislodged from the asteroid belt...
与地球交叉的轨道
into Earth-crossing orbits...
那么 就会有朝一日再次打击我们的星球
and, therefore, could again one day strike our planet.
虽然大多数潜在的有威胁的物体是小行星
Although most potentially hazardous objects are asteroids...
但是彗星依然是不可掉以轻心的威胁
comets remain a legitimate threat.
这些冰块 来自外太阳系
These icy bodies, which come from the outer solar system...
其速度要快于小行星3倍
can travel three times faster than asteroids...
因此它只需9个月
so it only takes nine months...
就可以从木星的轨道
for them to get from the orbit of Jupiter...
来到地球的轨道
to the orbit of Earth.
你不可能对彗星的撞击有提前几年的安排
You couldn't plan years ahead for an impact from most comets.
你获悉它有可能就是提前几个星期
You'd hear about it maybe a few weeks ahead...
最多就几个月
maybe months at the most.
幸运的是 木星充当了星际保护伞
Fortunately, Jupiter acts as a planetary shield.
它偏离或吸引了漂向地球的彗星
It deflects or absorbs comets that drift towards Earth.
科学家现在有了图像来予以证明
And scientists now have the pictures to prove it.
1994年7月22日 世界各地的望远镜
On July 22, 1994, telescopes around the world...
捕捉到了人类历史上
caught a glimpse of one of the most violent comet impacts...
最为激烈的彗星撞击的瞬间
in the history of humanity.
一串约20个名为苏梅克 列维9的彗星碎片
A string of about 20 comet fragments named Shoemaker-Levy 9...
闯入了木星上部的云层
crashed into the upper cloud decks of Jupiter...
速度比子弹快上百倍
at speeds a hundred times faster than a speeding bullet.
由于气体木星没有固体表面
Since gaseous Jupiter doesn't have a solid surface...
物体在其致密的大气层里减缓速度
the objects were slowed down by its thick atmosphere...
在空中爆炸
and exploded as airbursts...
产生的烟柱地球上都能看到
which created plumes that were visible from Earth.
在新墨西哥州的阿尔伯克基桑迪亚国家实验室里
At Sandia National Laboratories in Albuquerque, New Mexico...
物理学家马克.波斯罗及其同僚预计
physicist Mark Boslough and his colleagues had predetermined...
这种宇宙奇观可以在地球上
that this cosmic spectacle would be seen from Earth...
通过计算机模拟来观察
through computer simulations.
人们确实没有想到这能够观察到
People really did not expect this to be observable...
一定程度上是因为撞击点
partly because the location of the impacts...
实际上从地球的视角 超出了视界
were actually over the horizon, over the rim of Jupiter...
超出了木星的边缘
as viewed from the Earth.
我们模拟了碎片高速闯入...
We simulated the interaction of the fragments...
木星大气层的相互作用
with Jupiter's atmosphere at high velocity...
巨大的烟柱喷射进太空
and the giant plume that was ejected out into space...
能够看到升起在木星的地平线上方
and could be seen rising over Jupiter's horizon...
可以在地球上和哈勃望远镜上看到
as viewed from the Earth and from the Hubble Space Telescope.
依靠空中爆炸影响的新知识
Armed with new knowledge about airburst impacts...
波斯罗开始重新审视发生在我们星球上的类似事件
Boslough began reinvestigating a similar event...that happened on our planet.
1908年6月30日
On June 30, 1908...
人类历史上有记录的地球上最大的宇宙灾难
the biggest cosmic disaster in recorded human history...
发生在俄罗斯
on Earth occurred in Russia.
一个巨大的物体在西伯利亚偏僻的通古斯荒野里爆炸
A large object exploded in Siberia's remote Tunguska wilderness.
爆炸引发的热浪和冲击波
The blast ignited heat and shockwaves...
掀翻了800多平方公里范围内的8000万棵树木
which toppled 80 million trees over an 800-square mile area.
然而却没有一人直接被害 因为该地区人迹罕见
Yet no one was directly killed because few people lived in the area.
通古斯大灾难困惑了科学家将近一个世纪
The Tunguska disaster had baffled scientists for almost a century...
因为没有撞击坑或陨石坑被发现
because no impact crater or meteorite has been found.
该地区许多树木被夷为平地
And many of the trees in the area were flattened...
但是却没有燃烧
but not incinerated.
许多科学家最终得出结论
Many scientists finally came to the conclusion...
一块太空石块在闯入我们大气层后
that a space rock exploded as an airburst...
在空中发生了爆炸
when it hit our atmosphere.
因此这是个大气层爆炸
So this was an atmospheric explosion.
它是唯一的一次
It was really the only one we knew about...
我们知道看似反常
which made it seem unusual...
却非常类似于木星撞击
very much like the Jupiter impact...
然而事实上 这些可能要比我们认为的
and that, in fact, these are probably more common...
更为常见
than we had really thought.
这颗小行星
The asteroid was originally calculated...
原先计算为直径200英尺
to be 200 feet in diameter...
释放出10到15兆吨的能量
and released 10 to 15 megatons of energy...
是基于该地区的破坏计算出来的
based on the devastation in the area.
然而波斯罗现在认为其个头要小得多
But Boslough now thinks the size was much smaller.
在我做15兆吨撞击的模拟时
When I did the simulation with a 15-megaton impactor...
火球 爆炸产生的高温气体
the fireball, the very hot gas that emerged from the explosion...
会各个方向散落到地面
descended all the way to the surface.
那将焚毁所有的树木
That would have incinerated all the trees...
造成这个区域完全焚毁
and created this zone of complete devastation...
那并不是通古斯所见到的情景
that was not observed at Tunguska.
树木并没有焚烧
The trees were not incinerated.
因此 其规模将不得不低于
Therefore, the mass would've had to have been...
人们原先的想象
less than people had previously thought.
波斯罗设计了新的模拟
Boslough designed new simulations...
显示出是空中爆炸的冲力作用
to show that the momentum effect of the air blast...
不是石块的大小 造成了灾难
not the size of the rock, caused the devastation.
我模拟了一个物体以35度角闯入
I modeled this as an object coming in at a 35-degree angle...
我让它在落下
and l exploded it when it descended...
到离地7 8英里处爆炸
below about seven or eight miles above the surface.
它闯入 爆炸
It comes in, explodes...
但是热物质喷射继续下降
but the jet of hot material continues to descend.
这样你看到的是爆炸后的冲力作用
So what you see is the momentum effect after the explosion.
冲力是一种速度
The momentum is the velocity...
继续携带力量往下
that continues to carry the mass downward...
直到它最终偃旗息鼓
before it finally slows down and stops.
波斯罗的最新模拟还证明了事实上
Boslough's new simulations also account for the fact...
地形并不平坦
that the terrain was not flat...
因此爆炸产生的风被山脊给增强了
so the winds from the blast were amplified by the ridgelines.
阵风在山脊顶部更强些
The gust is stronger on the top of the ridge...
刚好超过山脊顶部
and just beyond the top of the ridge.
而在那里你会看到最多的树木
That's where you would tend to have the most trees...
最大的危害
and the most damage.
波斯罗的最新研究
Boslough's new research...
可能意味着 发现较小的小行星
may mean that finding smaller asteroids...
要比原先想象的更为重要
is more important than previously thought.
从这项研究得到的结论之一
One of the conclusions that results from this work...
就是较小的小行星可以在地表产生可观的破坏
is that smaller asteroids can create significant damage at the surface.
并不在于是否会 而是在于何时遭到
It's not a matter of if, but when we'll be hit...
另一次通古斯物体的打击
by another Tunguska object.
据估计每500年就会发生一次
It's estimated to happen once every 500 years.
由于地球如今人口更多
And with Earth being more populated today...
因此打击将会更加致命
such an impact could be deadly.
小行星和彗星撞击不是过去的事件
Asteroid and comet impacts are not events of the past.
它们从没停止 有朝一日会再次
They're ongoing, and one day could again...
深刻改变地球上的生命
profoundly alter life on Earth.
信不信由你 地球每天都会遭到
Believe it or not, Earth takes a hit...
足球般大小的太空石块的打击
from soccer ball-sized space rocks every day.
大多数来无声息
Most go unseen.
然而在1992年 业余摄像机捕捉到了一颗陨石
But in 1992, amateur video caught a meteorite...
闪烁划过夜空
flash across the nighttime sky.
它最终砸碎了纽约郊外的停着的
It eventually crushed the back end of a parked car...
一辆汽车的屁股
in suburban New York.
被小陨石甚至大陨石击中的几率是极其低的
The odds of being struck by small or even large meteorites...are extremely low.
但是潜在的危害都会让航天局保持高度警惕
But the potential harm one could cause keeps NASA on high alert.
国会授权航天局必须查明九成以上
Congress mandated that NASA must detect...
直径超过半英里的近地物体
over 90 percent of near-Earth objects...over a half-mile in diameter.
这些石块打击地球的能量
These rocks could strike the Earth with the energy...
有可能超过我们星球现在核武器的总和
greater than all the nuclear weapons on our planet today.
迄今最具威胁的近地小行星是阿波菲斯
The most potentially hazardous near-Earth asteroid to date...
它相当于一个大的城市街区
is Apophis, which is the size of a large city block.
这块太空石头将会在2029年4月13号掠过地球
This space rock will make a close pass near Earth on April 13, 2029.
阿波菲斯大约有
Apophis has a one in about 45,000 chance...
4.5万分之一的概率撞击地球
of impacting the Earth.
那引起了一定程度的担忧
That is cause for at least some concern...
即使概率非常低
even though the probabilities are very low.
并非所有的小行星都是那么大
It's not all that big as asteroids go...
但是一旦它落在哪座城市头上 那座城市就将有灭顶之灾
but if it were to fall on a city, it would obliterate the city.
这虽然是微乎其微的可能性 但并不是零
It's still a miniscule probability, but it's not zero.
我认为真正的妙计就是在上面安放一个转发器
I think a really good idea is to put a transponder on it...
可以用来极其精准地跟踪它
that can be used to track it very accurately.
这样我们就可以知道它是否具有威胁
Then we can know if it's a threat or not.
科学家正在研发缓解技术
Scientists are developing mitigating technologies...
来彻底摧毁阿波菲斯这样的近地小行星
to either destroy a near-Earth asteroid like Apophis...
或将其推出威胁的路径
or nudge it out of harm's way.
不过虽说小行星和彗星威胁生命
But as much as asteroids and comets are life-threatening...
但是它们也有可能有朝一日拯救生命
they also could one day be lifesaving.
我们也可以以利用同样的技术
We also, with the same technology, have access...
来利用那些小行星实现其它的目的
to those asteroids for other purposes...
诸如发掘它们 把物质带回地球
such as mining them and retrieving materials to bring back to Earth.
行星科学家约翰.刘易斯毕生都在
Planetary scientist John Lewis has spent a career...
开发发掘太空宝贵资源的方法
devising methods for mining space for precious resources.
刘易斯称接近地球的小行星
Lewis says asteroids' proximity to Earth...
出现了一个机会 来获取它们的大量金属
present an opportunity to harvest their vast metal...
矿产 固态水为我们地球
mineral, and water ice for our planet...
以及未来的太空任务和定居所用
as well as future space missions and habitats.
我一直憧憬着
I always envision the use of space resources...
将太空资源带回地球
to bring back to Earth.
其中之一就是开采水资源
One of these is the extraction of water.
当然啦 水可以用来维持生命
The water can be used, of course, for life support.
你可以饮用它
You can drink it.
你也可以用来发电
You can also generate electric power.
在水里插入电极
Stick electrodes in the water...
将其电解成氢和氧
electrolyze it into hydrogen and oxygen...
利用氢和氧作为火箭的推进剂
and use the hydrogen and oxygen as rocket propellants...
来返回地球
for the return to Earth.
小行星的许多有价值的成分中有铁镍
Among the many valuable components...in asteroids is iron-nickel...
还有高价金属 如钴和铂
as well as highly priced metals such as cobalt and platinum.
这些都可以提取出来
These could be extracted...
打造地球上的各种东西
to construct a variety of things on Earth.
刘易斯称工程师可以在太空中
Lewis says engineers could build...
建造绕地加工厂
Earth-orbiting processing plants in space...
开展开采制造 如同能源生产一样
to carry on mining manufacturing as well as energy production.
我的想法是大量的这些结构材料
My concept is that a lot of these structural materials...
可以用来建造太阳能卫星
could be used in the process of putting up solar-power satellites...
以生产取之不竭的廉价清洁能源
to produce unlimited quantities of cheap electricity very cleanly.
这样我们就可以生产这种能源 送回地球
So we produce this power, beam it down to Earth.
登陆小行星并非完全是科幻
And landing on an asteroid is not complete science fiction.
2001年 近地小行星约会任务
In 2001, the Near-Earth Asteroid Rendezvous mission...
即所谓的NEAR 成为了首个飞船
known as NEAR, became the first spacecraft...
登陆一颗小行星 叫做爱神
to touch down on an asteroid, named Eros...
它当时距离地球1.9亿英里
which was then 190 million miles from Earth.
我们在最近几年里
We've had several successful missions...
有过若干次对近地小行星的成功的任务
to near-Earth asteroids in recent years...
感觉到这些物体可以造访
and the sense that these bodies are accessible...
我们可以轻而易举到达那里 获取样本 进行研究
that we can easily go there, pick up samples, and study them.
小行星和彗星与地球有过动荡不安的关系
Asteroids and comets have had a tumultuous relationship with Earth.
它们既是创造者 又是毁灭者
They've been both creators and destroyers.
有朝一日 它们可以也能够弥补我们枯竭的资源
One day, they may be even able to replenish our depleting resources.
尽管未来致命打击的机率
Although the odds of future deadly impacts...
要小于车祸或遭遇雷击
are less than getting in a car accident or being hit by lightning...
但是威胁始终高悬在我们星球的头上
the threat still looms over our planet.
我们该不该担忧小行星和彗星
Should we be worried about asteroids and comets...
在将来撞击地球呢?
impacting the Earth in the future?
这个 我们只想说 在未来的千年里
Well, let's just say that over the next thousand years...
有可能会有某种撞击
there might be some sort of an impact.
威胁不足以
The threat is not enough...
让你出去买小行星保险
to make you go out and buy asteroid insurance...
但是有可能有些东西是我们该予以关注的
but it's probably something we should pay some attention to.
我们知道纵贯历史
We know that throughout history...
地球一直遭到小行星的轰击
the Earth has been bombarded by asteroids.
毫无疑问它会在将来再次光顾
There's absolutely no doubt that it will occur again in the future.
问题不在于我们在未来是否会遭遇打击
The question is not whether we'll be struck in the future...
而是何时何地
But when and where